Inventory of the Huang Fu (黄孚) papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Huang Fu (黄孚) papers
1916-1937
72027
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes (2.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, reports, writings, and printed matter, relating to Chinese foreign relations, the 1927 incident at Nanjing, the Tanggu Truce settlement with Japan in 1933, domestic politics in China, Chiang Kai-shek, and the Nationalist government of China.
Huang, Fu, 1880-1936.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1972.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Huang Fu (黄孚) document the political activities of a government official and sworn "blood brother" of Chiang Kai-shek (蒋介石) during the early Republic of China period. The collection includes Huang's personal and official correspondence, reports, directives, speeches and writings, newspapers clippings and other posthumous materials.
In the early 1920s, Huang held such posts in Beijing such as acting foreign minister, acting premier and minister of education. During the Nanjing decade he served in multiple positions, including Shanghai mayor (1927), the National Government as minister of foreign affairs (1928), minister of the interior (1934) and chairman of the Beiping political affairs council (1933 to 1935).
Materials that relate to the fall of Cao Kun (曹锟) in the 1924 Beijing coup, when Huang Fu became acting premier of the Republic of China at the request of warlord Feng Yuxiang (冯玉祥), are in the Coup D'etat of 1924 File.
The Nanjing Incident (南京事件) file groups materials relating to the Incident which occurred in March 1927 when the National Revolutionary Army, comprised of both Kuomintang (KMT) and Communist troops, ransacked and looted foreign properties in Nanjing. This resulted in property damage and casualties of British, French and American citizens. Huang Fu played an instrumental role in negotiating settlements with the affected parties.
The Jinan Incident (济南事件) file includes materials relating to the May 3, 1928 armed conflict between the Japanese Army allied with Northern Chinese warlords against the KMT's southern army in Jinan, the capital of Shandong Province, during the Northern Expedition.
Documents relating to the Tanggu Truce (塘沽停战协定), a cease fire agreement signed on May 1, 1933, which ceded portions of northern Hebei Province to the Japanese, can be found in the Tangu Truce File, 1933-1934
In 1934, Huang Fu, in his capacity as commissioner in Northern China, had to mollify Japanese demands to restore railway and postal services between Manchuria and Northern China. Though Chiang Kai-shek (蒋介石) supported Huang's decision, the concession received considerable opposition within the government since the dealings lent de facto legitimacy to Japanese rule in Manchuria.
Lastly, papers deemed "private" include Huang's articles and public talks on Sino-Japanese relations affairs, as well incremental materials dealing specifically dealing with the resumption of postal and railway services in 1934 and the Nanjing Incident.
Biographical/Historical note
Biographical Note
1880 Born, in Zhejiang Province, China
1905-1908 Matriculated at Shimbu Gakko (military preparatory school) and joined Tongmenghui
1910 Graduated from Military Survey Academy in Tokyo, Japan Served as a topographer for the Military Advisory Bureau in Beijing
1912 Superintendent of base headquarters of the northern expeditionary forces
1915 Resided in Oakland, California
1916 Went to Shanghai to help plan military action in Zhejiang and assume post of military commissioner for the revolution troops there.
1917 Organized the National Peace Association
1918 Published Ou Zhan Zhi Jiao Xun yu Zhongguo zhi Jiang Lai ( Lessons of the European War and the Future of China)
1919 Published Zhan Hou Zhi Shi Jie ( The World After the War), a series of lectures he gave in Tianjin
1920 Served as consultant in the presidential office and director of the Chinese economic investigation bureau Published Ou Zhan Hou Zhongguo: Jingji yu Jiaoyu (China After the European War: Economics and Education)
1921 Sent to the United States and Europe to study economic conditions
1922 Returned to Tianjin, China Served as acting foreign minister
1923 Appointed Minister of Education
1924 Vice Chairman of the financial rehabilitation commission
1927 Mayor of Shanghai from July 7 to August 12
1928 Member of the State Council and Minister of Foreign Affairs
1931 Organized the New China Reconstruction Society
1933 Established the Mokan Elementary School and organized the Mokan Countryside Improvement Association Chairman of the Peiping political affairs council where he facilitated the Tanggu Truce
1934 Appointed Minister of Interior
1936 Died of liver cancer in Shanghai, China on December 6
Chiang, Kai-shek, 1887-1975.; China--Foreign relations--Japan.; China--Foreign relations.; China--Politics and government--1912-1949.; Japan--Foreign relations--China.; Statesmen--China.
- Coup d'etat of 1924 file, 1924 年北京政变相关文件 (Box 1)
- Nanjing Incident file 南京事件相关文件, 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - Negotiations with Japan and France 中日中法谈判, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Negotiations with the Great Britain 中英谈判, 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - Negotiations with the United States 中美谈判，bulk, 1928 (Box 1)
- Jinan Incident file including correspondence about the armed conflict between the Japanese Army allied with Northern Chinese worlords against the Kuomintang's southern army in Japan, the capital of Shandong during the Kuomintang's Northern Expedition济南事件相关文件 （包括信件等）, 1928 (Box 1)
- Tanggu Truce file, draft history and personal memoirs 塘沽停战协定的历史及回忆录, 1933-1934 (Box 2)
- Railway and postal service file, documents relating to the resumption of service有关恢复通车通邮的文件, 1934 (Box 3)
- Correspondence file 通信往来, 1934-1935 (Box 3-4)
  - Wang Jingwei 汪精卫, 1933-1935 (Box 3)
  - Tang Youren 唐有壬, 1933-1935 (Box 3)
  - Chiang Kai-shek 蒋介石, 1933-1935 (Box 3)
  - He Yingqin 何应钦, 1933-1935 (Box 4)
  - Yang Yongtai 杨永泰, 1933-1935 (Box 4)
  - Zhang Qun 张群, 1933-1936 (Box 4)
  - Yin Tong 殷同, 1933-1935 (Box 4)
  - Yuan Liang 袁良, 1933-1935 (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous documents from the Central and local governments 来自中央及地方政府的文件, 1934 (Box 5)
- Private papers file 私人文件, 1916-1937 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence from Huang Xing 黄兴的来信, 1916-1934 (Box 6)
  - Yin Tong's report about his negotiation with Japan 殷同与日本谈判的报告, undated (Box 6)
  - Letters from Chiang Kai-shek 蒋介石的来信, 1927-1931 (Box 6)
  - Telegrams exchanged between Huang Fu, Chiang Kai-shek and others concerning the Jinan Incident 黄孚、蒋介石等讨论济南事件的电报, 1927-1928 (Box 6)
  - Draft proposal with regard to the reform of political, military and party affairs 关于政治、军事及党务改革的草案, undated (Box 6)
  - Huang Fu's telegrams to Chiang Kai-shek 黄孚发给蒋介石的电报, Mar.-Jul., 1927 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, includes letters and documents exchanged between Huang Fu, Wang Jiangwei, He Yingqin, and others 通讯（黄孚、汪精卫与何应钦之间的信件往来）, 1932-1935 (Box 6)
  - Telegrams from Huang Fu to Feng Yuxiang and others including the "June 21, 1927" message 黄孚发给冯玉祥和其他人的电报（包括1927年6月21日的电报） (Box 6)
  - Speech by Huang Fu on the fourth anniversary of the establishment of the Municipal Government of Shanghai 黄孚在庆祝上海市政府成立四周年的庆典上的讲话, undated (Box 6)
  - Telegrams and documents about Jinan Incident 关于济南事件的电报和文件, 1928 (Box 6)
  - Telegrams exchanged between Huang Fu and others during the period he was in charge of Zheng Zheng Hui (Political Reconstruction Council) in Beijing 黄孚和他人的电报往来（在其任北平政务整理委员会委员长期间）, 1933-1935 (Box 6)
  - Messages exchanged between Huang Fu and others about the negotiation of Tanggu Incident 黄孚和其他人有关塘沽事件的通讯, 1933 (Box 6)
  - Documents relating to Jinan Incident and Nanjing Incident 济南事件和南京事件的相关文件, 1927-1928 (Box 6)
  - Personal letters 私人信件, 1929-1937 (Box 6)
  - Letters from Feng Yuxiang, Duan Qirui and others 冯玉祥、段祺瑞和其他人的来信, 1924-1926 (Box 6)
  - Telegrams exchanged between Chiang Kai-shek and Huang Fu, includes Chiang's condolence to Mrs. Huang on Huang Fu's death 蒋介石和黄孚的电报往来 （包括蒋介石向黄孚夫人对黄孚去世表示慰问）, 1936 (Box 6)
  - Letters from Huang Fu to his wife 黄孚写给夫人的信, 1920-1933 (Box 6)
- Speeches and writings file 黄孚演说与写作文件, 1918-1932 (Box 7)
- Clippings file, includes newspapers and magazine articles about Huang Fu, with emphasis on the negotiations between China and Japan about the resumption of postal and railway services between China proper and Manchuria 黄孚收集的剪报（包括报纸和杂志，主要是中日关于恢复通车通邮）, 1933-1935 (Box 7)